Finding Aid for Susan W. Kaufmann papers, 1995-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Susan W. Kaufmann papers 1995-2011
Kaufmann, Susan W.
2012075 Aa 2
Susan W. Kaufmann served as the Associate Director for Advocacy at the University of Michigan’s Center for the Education of Women. The collection documents her involvement with the Ann Arbor Mayor’s Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women, later the Washtenaw County Coalition on Gender Violence and Safety, and her research on the potential impact of the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative (also known as Proposal 2). The material includes extensive research and press clippings related to the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative, in addition to copies of presentations, correspondence, and other material related to Proposal 2.
5.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received as part of the accession of records coming from the University of Michigan Center for Education of Women (donor no. 6885 ) in March 2012 and in February 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In her capacity as Associate Director at the University of Michigan’s Center for the Education of Women (CEW), Susan Kaufmann has been heavily involved in a number of organizations in Michigan that seek to further the rights of women and encourage diversity.
From 1995-2004, Kaufmann led the Ann Arbor Mayor’s Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women, which became known as the Washtenaw County Coalition on Gender Violence around 2000. The Task Force was founded in 1995 when Ann Arbor took a stand on the issue of violence against women. Housed first in the City Administrator’s Office and later in the Ann Arbor Police Department, the Task Force was charged with coordinating a variety of local agencies, law enforcement and community organizations in order to address and prevent violence against women. In addition to developing a public outreach and education program, the Task Force also created the Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner (SANE) program to help improve nursing care and forensic evidence collection following sexual assaults. They also created the Sexual Assault Response Team to bring together specially trained medical, law enforcement, and advocacy professionals; placed safety phones in central Ann Arbor; and improved coordination between law enforcement, health care, and service and advocacy organizations.
Kaufmann also conducted research on the potential impact of the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative, drawing on her findings of impact in California and Washington following passage of similar ballot initiatives banning affirmative action and equal opportunity programs. Known as Proposal 2, the 2006 ballot initiative was proposed by the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative Committee and endorsed by Ward Connerly, the California businessman who led a similar campaign to end affirmative action in California with Proposition 209. The executive director of the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative Committee was Jennifer Gratz, the plaintiff in the Supreme Court case that ruled that the University of Michigan’s undergraduate admissions policy was unconstitutional. The ballot initiative passed in 2006 by a vote of 58% to 42% but was subsequently challenged by various civil rights organizations. As of May 2012, the full Sixth Circuit is still reviewing those challenges. Kaufmann’s research was of interest to One United Michigan, a coalition formed to defeat the proposal, as well as to many other organizations and news sources.
The Susan W. Kaufmann collection documents her involvement with the Ann Arbor Mayor’s Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women, later the Washtenaw County Coalition on Gender Violence and Safety, and her research on the potential impact of the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative (also known as Proposal 2). The collection is divided into two series: Ann Arbor Mayor's Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women (0.2 linear feet) and Michigan Civil Rights Initiative (4.8 linear feet).
Subjects:
Connerly, Ward, 1939-; Kaufmann, Susan W.; Affirmative action programs--California.; Affirmative action programs--Michigan.; Civil rights--Michigan.; Constitutional amendments--Michigan.; Race discrimination--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Women--Crimes against.; Michigan Civil Rights Initiative.; One United Michigan (Organization); University of Michigan. Center for the Education of Women.
- Ann Arbor Mayor's Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women
  The Ann Arbor Mayor's Task Force on Increasing Safety for Women series documents Kaufmann's activities with the Task Force. Material in this series includes documents distributed by the Task Force, member lists, minutes, presentations, and press clippings.
  - About the Task Force (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1997-1999 (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Member Lists (Box 1)
  - Member Satisfaction Survey (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1995-1999 (Box 1)
  - Presentation to the Ann Arbor Police Department 2002 (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings (Box 1)
  - Printed Materials (Box 1)
  - Report to City Council 1996 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Plan 1999 (Box 1)
- Michigan Civil Rights Initiative
  The Michigan Civil Rights Initiative series documents Kaufmann's involvement with groups that worked to defeat Proposal 2. It is principally composed of material collected by Kaufmann as part of her research related to Proposal 2 and the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative. The Michigan Civil Rights Initiative series is further divided into five subseries: Background, California, Campaign Files, Press Clippings, and Impact.
  - Background
    The Background subseries contains material collected by Kaufmann as part of her research, including articles, reports, and statistics related to subject areas such as affirmative action and segregation. It also includes material related to the repercussions of similar initiatives in other states.
    - Affirmative Action, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies (Box 1)
    - Demographics (Box 1)
    - Diversity, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Florida (Box 1)
    - Graduate Program Statistics, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - MCRI (Box 2)
    - Post Proposition 2 Research (Box 2)
    - Racism (Box 2)
    - Research Compilations (Box 2)
    - Residential Segregation (Box 2)
    - Segregation (Box 2)
    - Texas (Box 2)
    - Ward Connerly (Box 2)
    - Washington
      - Analysis (Box 2)
      - Contracting (Box 2)
      - Faculty Employment (Box 2)
      - General (Box 2)
      - K-12 (Box 2)
  - California
    The California subseries contains material collected by Kaufmann related to Ward Connerly's campaign for Proposition 209 in California and its after effects. Documents in this subseries include reports, statistics, press clippings, and other articles related to Proposition 209.
    - Cal State System (Box 2)
    - Civil Service (Box 2)
    - Contracting (Box 2)
    - Diversity (Box 2)
    - Education (Box 2)
    - Employment (Box 2)
    - Faculty Hiring (Box 2)
    - Graduation Rates (Box 2)
    - Higher Education, Diversity, and Access Commissioned Research (Box 3)
    - Lawsuits (Box 3)
    - National Coalition of Free Men (Box 3)
    - Programs Affected by 209 (Box 3)
    - Proposition 209 Analysis, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Sports (Box 3)
    - Undergraduate Admissions, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - University of California Statistics (Box 3)
    - Women (Box 3)
  - Campaign Files
    The Campaign Files are composed of material related to One United Michigan and other groups that actively campaign against Proposal 2. It also includes material related to Kaufmann's activities and presentations given by her related to the Michigan Civil Rights initiative. Documents in this subseries include clippings, copies of presentations, talking points, and campaign handouts.
    - Amicus Briefs, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign Guidelines (Box 3)
    - Campaign Materials (Box 3)
    - Connerly 2010 (Box 3)
    - Contacts (Box 3)
    - Decision Guide 2006 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Free Press Editorial Board (Box 4)
    - Handouts (Box 4)
    - Impact 209 (Box 4)
    - Mark Perry (Box 4)
    - MCRI Language, Paper, Presentation (Box 4)
    - Media, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - New Directions Article (Box 4)
    - Opposition (Box 4)
    - Presentations and Outreach
      - ACLU Michigan 2003 (Box 4)
      - Educational Outreach (Box 4)
      - Crossing Boundaries 2008 (Box 4)
      - Eisenhower Foundation 2007 (Box 4)
      - Gender 2006-2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Michigan Business and Professional Association Talk 2007 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Civil Rights Summit 2006 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Diversity Summit 2008 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Tech 2006 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Women's Summit 2005, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
      - Race 2006 (Box 4)
      - Rowley-Bowman Seminar 2007 (Box 4)
      - Speaking Engagements and Logistics (Box 4)
      - Toward A Fair Michigan debates 2006 (Box 4)
      - Traverse City 2006 (Box 4)
    - Race and Gender Referendum Talking Points (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Materials (Box 5)
      - 2004-2008, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Center for Equal Opportunity (Box 5)
      - Outreach programs 2005 (Box 5)
  - Press Clippings
    The Press Clippings subseries contains press clippings related to the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative, Proposal 2, and articles by and about Susan Kauffmann.
    - Affirmative Action (Box 5)
    - Detroit Free Press Op-Ed June 2006 (Box 5)
    - MCRI, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Post Proposition 2 New, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Super Tuesday 2007-2008 (Box 5)
    - Supreme Court Decision June 1993 (Box 5)
    - Susan Kaufmann Coverage (Box 5)
  - Impact (Box 6)
    The Impact subseries contains analyses and documentation of impact of the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative legislation on Michigan's economy, business, and higher education, and includes academic articles (some by Kaufmann), reports by various organizations, and coverage of MCRI-related lawsuits.
    - Analysis
      - Academic (Box 6)
      - Michigan Civil Rights Commission (Box 6)
      - Senate Fiscal Agency (Box 6)
    - Economic Impact (Box 6)
    - Implementation (Box 6)
    - Lawsuits 2001, 2003-2009, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - On Contracting business (Box 6)
    - On Higher education (Box 6)